Machlup, Fritz; Papers ger125
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Fritz Machlup Papers
1935-1982
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Machlup, Fritz, 1902-1983
ger125
0.5 cubic ft.
The Fritz Machlup Papers contian a partial collection of his published writings as a professor of economics and international finance.
Biographical History
Fritz Machlup, professor of economics and international finance, was born in Wiener-Neustadt, Austria on December 15, 1902. Machlup received his doctorate under Ludwig von Mises at the University of Vienna in 1923 and had already published four books and over 150 articles before 1935. Fleeing Hitler and the National Socialists, Machlup first arrived in the United States in September 1933 on a student visa. He was offered a one-year teaching position at Harvard University in 1934 and formally emigrated to the U.S. in 1935. Machlups distinguished teaching career included the University at Buffalo, NY (1935-1947), Johns Hopkins University (1947-1960), and Princeton University (1960-1971), as well as visiting professorships at universities in Europe, Japan and Australia. In addition to his teaching and research activities, Machlup was the founder in 1963 of the Bellagio Group, a collaborative of scholars from the United States and Italy, which acted as consultants to the U.S. Department of the Treasury during the late 1960s and early 1970s. Fritz Machlup died in Princeton, New Jersey on January 30, 1983.
Scope and Contents
The Fritz Machlup Papers is a partial collection of the published writings of Machlup, 1935-1982. It consists of reprints of his articles and encyclopedia entries primarily in German and English, but also contains translations into French and Hungarian. The main collection of materials pertaining to Fritz Machlup is located at the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, Stanford University.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series, arranged chronologically
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2006.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Economists--United States; Publications; Machlup, Fritz, 1902-1983
- "Inflation and Decreasing Costs of Production.", 1935 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 1)
- "On the Meaning of the Marginal Product.", 1937 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 2)
- "On the Meaning of the Marginal Product.", 1937 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 3)
- "The Optimum Lag of Imitation Behind Innovation.", 1958 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 4)
- "Why Not Hahnism?", 1959 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 5)
- "Der Weltstreit zwischen Mikro- und Makrotheorien in der Nationalkonomie.", 1960 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 6)
- "Erfindung und technische Forschung.", 1960 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 7)
- "Monopol.", 1960 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 8)
- "Oligopol.", 1961 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 9)
- "Die Plne zur Reform des internationalen Geldwesens.", 1962 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 10)
- "Patentwesen (I).", 1962 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 11)
- "Patentwesen (II).", 1962 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 12)
- "Polypol.", 1963 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 13)
- "Wettbewerb (III).", 1963 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 14)
- "Die Produktivitt der naturwissenschaftlichen und technischen Forschung und Entwicklung.", 1963 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 15)
- "International Economic Co-operation.", 1964 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 16)
- Strategies in the War on Poverty.", 1965 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 17)
- Real Adjustment, Compensatory Corrections, and Foreign Financing of Imbalances in International Payments.", 1965 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 18)
- "International Monetary Systems and the Free Market Economy.", 1966 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 19)
- "LHomo Oeconomicus et ses Collgues", 1967" Homo Oeconomicus and his Class Mates.", 1970 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 20)
- "Patents.", 1968 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 21)
- "If Matter Could Talk.", 1969 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 22)
- "Academic Freedom.", 1971 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 23)
- "Financing, Correcting, and Adjustment: Three Ways to Deal with an Imbalance of Payments" Photocopy.", 1971 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 24)
- "Tenure in Colleges and Universities.", 1971 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 25)
- "Changes in the International Monetary System and the Effects on Banks.", 1971 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 26)
- "Comment.", 1972 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 27)
- "Nationalism, Provincialism, Fixed Exchange Rates and Monetary Union.", 1972 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 28)
- "The Universal Bogey.", 1972 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 29)
- "The Expanded Role of SDRs and the Possibility of an SDR Standard.", 1972 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 30)
- "Internationale Liquiditt.", 1973 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 31)
- "Learning More About Knowledge.", 1973 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 32)
- "The Effects of Fiscal Policy and the Choice of Definitions.", 1973 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 33)
- "The Illusion of Universal Higher Education.", 1974 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 34)
- "Integrationshemmende Integrationspolitik.", 1974 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 35)
- "International Monetary Systems.", 1975 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 36)
- "Between Outline and Outcome the Reform was Lost.", 1976 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 37)
- "Wrdigung der Werke von Friedrich A von Hayek.", 1977 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 38)
- "Explaining Changes in Balances of Payments and Foreign-Exchange Rates: A Polemic without Graphs, Algebra, and Citations.", 1980 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 39)
- "Hayek, Friedrich A von.", 1979 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 40)
- "The Economic Cost of Knowledge.", 1980 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 41)
- "Beruhzsok az emberi erforrsokba s a producktv tudsba",; Hungarian translation of "Investment in Human Resources and Productive Knowledge.", 1982 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 42)
- "Austrian Economics.", 1982 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 43)
- Growth Rates, Trade Balances, and Exchange Rates.", 1982 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 44)
- Marginal Revenue.", 1982 (Box 1 (Fritz Machlup Papers ), Folder 45)